Inventory of the Herman Recht Papers 1943-1946
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Folders 101-200: 31 January 1944-6 June 1944
  - (2)
    - Folders 171-180: 13 May 1944-20 May 1944 (2, 8)
      Is told that his chances at making officer would be better if he were a 2nd or 1st class petty officer; asks for gossip from back home. Any promotion is stalled for three weeks because the officer he talked to has left for California. Puts in a request for leave in mid-June, but leaves are still frozen; reading “Release from Nervous Tension,” by Dr. D.H. Fink. Does not think it sensible for Esther to move down to Williamsburg. His superior gets transferred out, and replaced with a new boss. New boss holds a conference with Recht, telling him that both he and his old boss, Wilson, know that he is working under his capabilities, and they will try to transfer him someplace with a better chance for advancement; his new boss is friends with the procurement officer, the one in charge of rerating and taking application for promotions; talks about how some enlisted men were punished for sunning themselves while on duty. One of the members of Recht’s office gets rerated ahead of him; proposes to reorganize the entire system of filing memoranda. Would consider Navy work in Europe as a yeoman; talks about the trial of some seditionists. Is told by his new boss that Esther come down every month, and he will be given time off. Sees the movie “Gaslight” with Ingrid Bergman and Charles Boyer; talks about a contest for Postwar Economic Programs.
      Subseries 9: Folders 181-190: 21 May 1944- 28 May 1944
    - Folders 181-190: 21 May 1944- 28 May 1944 (2, 9)
      Comments on his appreciation of Virginius Dabney and the Richmond Times-Dispatch. Reads the book “Germany Will Try It Again,” by Schultz. Sees a Betty Grable movie, with her and other women performing a gun drill; comments about how he is much happier being in the service than merely being a civilian; theorizes about the end of the war and what will come after; talks about a program for former Navy prisoners at the camp. Still does not know about his rerate; wants to parlay his organization of memoranda into a system for the whole camp. Gets an article from Esther about the Jews in Palestine. A book Recht requested, “Better Eyesight without Glasses” comes into the library, so he can try and improve for his officer test; Begins preparing for the takeover of Camp Peary by the regular Navy, on 29 May. Sees the movie “Story of Dr. Wassel,” with Gary Cooper; thinks about going to see Virginius Dabney give the Commencement address at the College of William and Mary; muses how long the world will be in turmoil unless it becomes better able to handle crises. Gets a letter from the ACLU asking for donations; gets his index shown to the Lieutenant.
      Subseries 10: Folders 191-200: 29 May 1944-6 June 1944
    - Folders 191-200: 29 May 1944-6 June 1944 (2, 10)
      Enjoys getting gossip from home. New changes in liberty schedules and a new Personal Inspection of each department, as part of the switchover into Navy control; talks about the trials the new lieutenant is having in replacing Lt. Wilson. New lieutenant, Lt. Crockett, wants to help Recht get his commission, even though the Navy is overcrowded with lawyers; sees the movie “Outward Bound.” Has a conversation with a friend about the current problems, as Recht is his friend’s only intellectual outlet. One of Recht’s friends from home is assigned to Camp Peary; gets another man added to his department, as well as a new ensign; sees the movie “Between Two Worlds.” Baby-sits for Lt. Crockett at his house on the York River; as he is taking Recht back to the Barracks, Crockett and Recht talk more about his commissioning. The new ensign offers to buy the men in the department cokes. Talks about the invasion of France by the Allies. Asks Esther about the perception of anti-”negro” sentiment in the Navy, and then explains what he knows about it. Hears a man in the office suggest that there is anti-”negro” and anti-Semitic feelings in the armed forces, and the best plan would be to send then to Africa and Palestine, but eventually gives up the argument because it is not going anywhere.
  Series 3: Folders 201-300: 7 June1944- 25 September 1944
- Folders 201-300: 7 June1944- 25 September 1944
  - (3)
      Subseries 1: Folders 201-210: 7 June 1944-21 June 1944
    - Folders 201-210: 7 June 1944-21 June 1944 (3, 1)
      Hears about the government drilling for oil in Point Barrow, Alaska; sees Life pictures of the war in Europe. Talks about the fears everyone has now that the invasion has happened. Details the bus schedule for him coming home on leave. Talks about how landlords in Williamsburg and Yorktown overcharge the Navy personal because they are only there for a short time; asks Esther about the Clairton swimming pool, which is having race problems. Talks about the name of the new Camp Peary newspaper, the Peary Scope. Lt. Crockett sets up an interview between Recht and Lt. Maul, the procurement officer, to talk about his possible commission; makes fun of the other people in his unit for how young they are. Talks about soldiers caught using black market gas. Goes on leave to Clairton; lost his bag on the way back, but it was found.
      Subseries 2: Folders 211-220: 22 June 1944-29 June 1944
    - Folders 211-220: 22 June 1944-29 June 1944 (3, 2)
      All rerates are now subject to regular Navy policies, which include taking an exam. Finds it harder to readjust to life at Camp Peary this time as opposed to others. Gets complimented by the Asst. Commander of the base during an inspection of 1,500-1,700 Navy personnel; sees “Going My Way” with Bing Crosby and Barry Fitzgerald, and hears a pianist play. Lt. Crockett asks him to help write a letter for a man in the department who wants to be discharged because his wife is not feeling well; the Red Cross is checking into requests for leave and discharge because of family members getting ill, because of fake illnesses; the Asst. Commander’s plan to have all the Seabees take tests to become regular Navy soldiers is put on hold when the Commander finds out, without having been consulted. Has finally finished his backlog of work from over his leave; runs into a group of Italian prisoners of war; talks about the Russian offensive and that state of the German army. The old assistant commander of the base is reassigned for trying to usurp the power of the commander; doctors and dentists under 38 are being told to enlist or risk being drafted as privates. Is told by the rerate yeoman that it will be near impossible for him to skip ratings to Y3c. Talks about the death of one of his friends from home, and how it affected him. Becomes a semi-official letter writer for his department.
      Subseries 3: Folders 221-230: 30 June 1944-4 July 1944
    - Folders 221-230: 30 June 1944-4 July 1944 (3)
      Includes a pay stub for Recht to the amount of $119. Calls a show of local talent a display of “hill-billy music;” talks about the nomination of Dewey and Bricker for the Republicans; discusses where the Jews will go after the war, with a possibility being Argentina. Talks more about Dewey and Bricker, and how, even though he has been back only 9 days, it seems much longer. The rumor is that Lt. Crockett is to be transferred out of Camp Peary because of his run-in with a Chief that has better connections; Capt. Ware, the commander of the camp, is fed up with the anti-Seabee sentiment among the regular navy officers on the base; talks about a Supreme Court case about 13 “negro” Seabees being declared unfit. 3 “negro”es have been assigned to the repair unit at Peary. Continues to speculate about the end of the war, talking with his friend Luiz; talks about the difference between Seabees and general service classifications. Takes care of one of his friends who has had more trouble than he adjusting to the service. He is completing his semi-annual report on himself; there is more speculation of Crockett being transferred. Sees the movie “Bathing Beauty,” with Esther Williams. Talks about the substantial gains in the army with regards to race, in comparison to how strict the military is.
      Subseries 4: Folders 231-240: 5 July 1944-11 July 1944
    - Folders 231-240: 5 July 1944-11 July 1944 (3, 4)
      Explains his pay stub for June; Had a Fourth of July event, which included a band, a chorus, actors playing presidents, a boxing match, and a wrestling match; considers buying some luggage. A friend of his, Fuss, is trying to get into the psychiatric clinic at Peary, to be a worker; Lt. Crockett is promoted to full Lieutenant; questions the people who thinks war should be ethical and gentlemanly. Crockett is going to help Recht by filling out his report in a way that emphasizes the areas that Recht is the best at; talks about having to turn in his Seabee uniform for regular navy ones, and the loss of comfortable shoes. Reading Rex Warner’s “Return of the Traveller[sic];” notes an anger in the literature of this war that was not present in the literature of WWI. Hears rumors about a friend of his learning Croatian and going to Cairo, and wonders what that means. Is hoping to get a tan for when Esther comes to visit. Talks about “robot bombs” being used by the Germans in Europe; questions who to blame for the war; feels that none of the real problems are being solved by the war; talks about the upcoming presidential campaign. Babysits for Lt. Crockett again; is informed that as of 2 July he has been rerated to S1c.
      Subseries 5: Folders 241-250: 11 July 1944-17 July 1944
    - Folders 241-250: 11 July 1944-17 July 1944 (3, 5)
      Tells Esther that he never intends to return to Williamsburg after he is discharged; discuss how he resents those civilians who do not know what the serviceman has given up by being in the military. Thinks that the Democrats are going to drop Wallace as FDR’s Vice President; having the African-American soldiers at the Camp has proved not to be a problem. The newest rumor is that the camp is to be condemned by the medical officers and moved to Ft. Eustis. Learns that there are no longer waivers on commissions, so his eyes must be correctable to 20/20; learns that Lt. Crockett is being replaced by a new Lt., Lt. Kennedy; visits the College Library. Finds out that he will not be commissioned anytime soon, because his eyes are too bad. Talks with one of the camp librarians, learning that many of the political books they used to carry have been removed; sees the movie “The Canterville Mystery;” talks about the mindset of the Germans in using the V-1 rockets; notices Jewish periodicals in the W&M library. Walks around the campus of William and Mary; resigns himself to his low rate and vows to enjoy the reading that he can get done instead; talks about an interview he read with Santayana. Says he feels like writing a book about his experience at Peary. Defends VP Wallace against being a liberal and an unrealistic idealist; dismisses the idea that, if Ester were to come to Williamsburg, she would work at Eastern State Hospital.
      Subseries 6: Folders 251-260: 18 July-26 July 1944
    - Folders 251-260: 18 July-26 July 1944 (3, 6)
      Writes a letter on the back of an old Outgoing Dispatch form; has a going-away dinner for Lt. Crockett. Is now reading Willard Price’s “Japan’s Islands of Mystery;” talks about the “German Army leaders revolt,” referring to the July 20 plot; talks about the Japanese home situation. Listens to parts of the Democratic National Convention on the radio; speculates about the relationship between FDR’s interest in the Pope and the US’s official stance towards Loyalist Spain, DeGaulle, and the Italian king. Hears that Truman has won the Vice Presidency nomination from the Democrats. Goes to see the movie “The Mask of Dimitrios;” comments on the factors that he thinks led to the nomination of Truman over Wallace. Talks about registering for classes at the camp, and how most people are using them as a spring-board to being a petty officer; mentions a quote of Churchill saying that the war will be over sooner than previously thought; talks about the possibility of racial problems if the economy goes bad. Keeps getting in discussions with the boys around the barracks about the “negro matter.” Hears from Russian writers grumblings about the lack of progress the Allied armies are making in Normandy. Talks about an oil drought at the camp; talks about the organization of the camp library, and how it is designed to be as uncontroversial as possible.
      Subseries 7: Folders 261-270: 26 July-1 August 1944
    - Folders 261-270: 26 July-1 August 1944 (3, 7)
      Is reading a book that provides a different view on Germany than the tradition ‘racist’ notions; talks about the Russians attacking Lwow, the Polish name for Lviv, which is the hometown of Recht’s parents. Reads in the College library about race issues in other camps in the US; talks about the amount of federal lawyers that were appointed; wonders about what will happen in Germany at the end of the war. States that there are good reasons for the Americans hating the Japanese more than the Germans; talks to the new Lt., Lt. Kennedy; complains about the removal of liberal magazines from the PX, but not conservative ones. Talks about his loneliness at the Camp, and how it is not affecting him too much; talks about 10 new African-Americans that have been received to work on the railroad. Talks about the racism that some of the white soldiers have towards the new men; intends to read Virginius Dabney’s books. Reads an editorial by Dabney questioning the reading habits of men in the service; meets with the chief in charge of the Camp library, about the history and future of the said library. Sees the movie “Storm over Lisbon;” talks with his barracks mates about what should be done to the Germans after the war; talks more about segregation in the camp. Talks about the Catholic chaplain’s attempt to get Maugham’s book “The Razor’s Edge” out of the camp library for being anti-Catholic. Mentions a feeling amongst men in service departments that they are not doing enough for the war, unlike the combat units. Reads about the founding of the American Veterans Committee; talks about people complaining about a lack of consumer goods.
      Subseries 8: Folders 271-280: 2 August 1944-7 August 1944
    - Folders 271-280: 2 August 1944-7 August 1944 (3, 8)
      Meets a German national who works in the library, and describes his beliefs; sees the movie “Memphis Belle;” in a disconnected page 2, talks about the political climate of America. Hears bad reports of the classes men are taking to prepare for their test for a general service rating; sees “I Love a Soldier.” Talks about how young all the members of his department are. Some Waves are coming to Peary, but he does not know who they will be replacing. Reads a memo that there will be no discrimination in selecting people for advanced schooling; talks about the government’s response to the Philadelphia strike. If officially transferred from Seabees to general service, along with the rest of the people at the camp. Starts with physical training for general service; wonders about the problem of some of the men in his department losing their rating when they get checked for general service.
      Subseries 9: Folders 281-290: 8 August 1944-17 September 1944
    - Folders 281-290: 8 August 1944-17 September 1944 (3, 9)
      Sees the movie “Mrs. Skeffington;” is trying to take a more phlegmatic attitude towards Peary, because he expects some day to be transferred, and does not want to get too attached. Cannot keep up with the first batch of physical training. Writes about how he hopes Esther trip home from seeing him was good, after a month long gap in letters. There is a picture of Recht on the letter dated 13 Sept. 1944. Will try to get Camel cigarettes for people back home. Gets the edge of a hurricane that is going through the area. Says that he will get off work for the upcoming Yontif, or holiday days. Almost gets transferred to another department after 4 people in Repairs department get in trouble for taking a car into Williamsburg and getting in trouble with a corpsman; is trying to get rerated to Y3c; sees the “Gypsy Wildcat.” Gets in a new batch of seamen from Pennsylvania, who insist on calling Recht “sir.” Talks about the new chain of command under Lt. Kennedy.
      Subseries 10: Folders 291-300: 18 September 1944-25 September 1944
    - Folders 291-300: 18 September 1944-25 September 1944 (3, 10)
      Talks about the Rosh Hashanah services at the camp. Gets a letter from a friend at another camp. Mentions that the camp football team will be playing its games in the College’s football stadium; has a debate with someone in his office about why they are going to vote for Dewey as opposed to FDR; talks about the differing US and British plans for post-war Italy. Hears a rumor of Seabees being shipped to California; is trying to get an absentee ballot. Gets rerated to Y3c. Sees the movie “Kismet;” relates a story of a soldier whose wife had been told she was pregnant, but actually has a tumor. There is a new camp 15 minutes of calisthenics, reduced from 45 minutes. Writes about an unknown pamphlet that appeared in the camp library; talks about the mob of people at the Travis House for dinner after the camp football game; Peary won the football game against a pro team from Washington DC.
  Series 4: Folders 301-400: 25 September 1944-8 March 1945
- Folders 301-400: 25 September 1944-8 March 1945
  - (4)
      Subseries 1:
    - (4, 1)
      Hears that Lt. Kennedy refereed the football game, and that he was a pro ref and umpire in multiple sports before the service; talks about the German resilience and the German transportation infrastructure; hears rumors of the Allies wanting to force Germany to be an agricultural state after the war; talks about the Republican platform. Watched the movie “Casanova Brown.” Talks about a party some of the sailors there had after they found out they were being transferred. Talks about the Yom Kippur services; makes a point by refusing to cut in line at the mess after not having worked all day because of Yom Kippur. Sees the movie “Arsenic and Old Lace.” Hears from Lt. Kennedy that a lot of the men who have been in the department the longest will soon be shipped out. Is playing a lot of chess; sees the movie “The Master Race;” talks about an Estonian in the Navy. The library is no longer getting new books in. Watches an illegal craps game; talks about how some of the families of soldiers had to be moved out of Brown Hall at the College; talks about the Democratic campaigning.
      Subseries 2: Folders 311-320: 6 October 1944-12 October 1944
    - Folders 311-320: 6 October 1944-12 October 1944 (4, 2)
      Talks jokingly about the impropriety of the liberty yeoman. Has a large convoy to try and help put together. Goes up to Washington DC for the weekend; talks about broad social and political problems with one of his friends; talks about the captain’s personnel inspection. Enjoys a dinner with one of his friends in Washington; cannot enjoy the trip fully because he knows he has to go back to the service. Gets a form from the chief of personnel to fill out about the duties of the key people in his department. Talks about how he got noticed with his yeoman’s badge on the wrong arm on the train back from DC; talks about an incident between some white soldiers and a “colored” soldier on the same train ride. Talks about the coffee maker as a navy tradition; talks about the death of Wendell Willkie. Talks about where the Jews should go after the war. The chaplain’s car he used to use to get to his office is being reassigned, and so he must walk; considers buying a trench coat; notes that the camp is being emptied of soldiers with longer tenure, and does not think they will be replenished. Is going to be interviewed by a man from the Personnel department to evaluate the worth of their duties.
      Subseries 3: Folders 321-330: 12 October 1944-15 November 1944
    - Folders 321-330: 12 October 1944-15 November 1944 (4, 3)
      Talks to a “colored” soldier about Jim Crow laws on the buses on the camp. Comments on an author using language in one of his books; talks about “preventive” legal counsel. Wins the camp checkers tournament. A kitten somehow gets into the transportation office; the brother of one of his co-workers dies. Talks about the swing from the south as Democrat to Republican. Two of the men in his department are reassigned to storekeepers. Tries to listen to the Boston symphony over the radio; does his laundry, which only requires soaking; mentions Armistice Day, which turned into Veterans Day. Predictions that 500,000 more men will be inducted into the armed forces are on the radio; one of Recht’s co-workers believes this generation will be permanently mentally scarred; disagrees with a letter that says that almost all the soldiers know what they are fighting for. Goes and sees the movie “None but the Lonely Heart;” talks about China and its Communist party. Hears about a book titled “What the Negro Wants”.
      Subseries 4: Folders 331-340: 18 November 1944-9 December 1944
    - Folders 331-340: 18 November 1944-9 December 1944 (4)
      The office Recht works in is being painted. Stares at the moon and the stars, and calls it the treat of his evening. Describes dinner at the camp. Lt. Kennedy finds out about Recht’s ability to do quick mental addition and has fun with it. Goes and sees a performance of opera songs, including one from La Boehme. Is avoiding eating bread and potatoes. Hears about a telephone operators strike; sees the movie “March of Time”. Reflects on the war, it being December 7 1944 and therefore the 3 year anniversary of Pearl Harbor. Sees the movie “Thirty Seconds over Tokyo;” friend Joe tries to get suggestions to keep his son from being sent overseas. Talks about discharges on account of age; says how if he were to get out now, he would try to get into a business that is making money off of the war.
      Subseries 5: Folders 341-350: 10 December 1944-29 December 1944
    - Folders 341-350: 10 December 1944-29 December 1944 (4, 5)
      Talks about the lack of people reading real books, as opposed to Readers’ Digest. One letter includes a newspaper clipping of an article on war diaries. Describes one of his co-worker’s “moralistic” attitudes; wants to go to Richmond to hear Grace Moore. Hears about the Christmas liberty that the Captain is giving the camp. Sees “Sunday Dinner for a Soldier.” Camp is getting many new men in just before Christmas. Hears rumors that Peary will house German POWs. Sees “Woman in the Window” and describes more about the movie “30 Seconds over Tokyo”. Writes about the treatment of US POWs by the Japanese. Spends time with Esther in Williamsburg, explaining partially the break in letters.
      Subseries 6: Folders 351-360: 29 January 1945-3 February 1945
    - Folders 351-360: 29 January 1945-3 February 1945 (4, 6)